{
  "reference_number": "11730",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I think that saying because methane is a \"short-lived gas\" and therefore should not be included in a reduction target is a compete\n abrogation of what we need to do. Just because methane is a \"short-lived gas\" in no way means we must not reduce its emissions\n\n right now. If we permit methane to be emitted at the same levels now, it is still going to have a dramatic effect (up to 12 times more\n potent than carbon dioxide, I hear), as we will continue to pump the same amounts out... It is not going to solve the crisis! Methane\n *must* be included in greenhouse gas emission reduction targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but only by bringing forward the deadline -- we must not allow the target to be pushed further into the future."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "I have selected \"No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed\", but I do think that it should be permissible to *reduce*\n\n future budgets, and those are the only changes that should be permitted. I am totally against allowing future budgets to be\n increased."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but only downwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but with caveats. Considerations over economic and fiscal circumstances are all well and good, but these must not be permitted\nto be given primacy over social and environmental circumstances. For example, if there is a decision to be made with have both a\nbetter and a worse economic outcome, but an inversely affected social or environmental outcome, then the better social or\n\nenvironmental outcome should be chosen, rather then the better economic outcome."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, absolutely. Without a clear, transparent and public statement of intent on how budgets will be achieved, they will be\n\nmeaningless."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is of utmost importance that the role of tangata whenua must be strongly considered ad respected. Pakeha have come to Aotearoa\nNew Zealand in greatly dispossessed Maori of their tino rangatira. Maori have a guardianship role over Aotearoa, and that role must\n\nnot be put aside in any way."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government should have to publicly respond to, and provide rationale when it deviates from the Commissionâ€™s advice. The\nClimate Commission should also act as an independent watchdog, publishing progress reports and highlighting problems."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The government should be removed from choosing how may ETS units are available, since the government will necessarily be open\n\nto political influence."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
